Inventory of the Michal Mudry [Michal Mudry-Sebik] papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Michal Múdry papers
1939-2000
2006C1
Múdry, Michal
12 manuscript boxes (6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Radio broadcast scripts, correspondence, writings, memoranda, reports, and printed matter, relating mostly to Radio Free Europe broadcasts to Czechoslovakia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to sound recordings, video recordings, or motion picture material requires at least two weeks advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2006.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Beneš (Edvard) papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Osuský (Štefan) papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Peroutka (Ferdinand) papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Radio Free Europe records, Hoover Institution Archives
Slovak League of America Congress Resolution, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
11 May 1909 Born, Drétoma / Drietoma, Austro-Hungary
1930-1936 Studied at the Faculty of Law, Comenius University, Bratislava, Czechoslovakia
1936-1939 Public lawyer, Bratislava
1939 Married Jarmila Navaříková Emigrated to the U.S.
1939-1978 Member of Slovak and Czechoslovak émigré organizations in the U.S. throughout his career
1943-1944 Secretary to the former Czechoslovak Prime Minister Milan Hodža
1945-1947 A Slovak Democratic Party representative in the postwar Czechoslovak government
1948 Emigrated again to the U.S. after allegations of espionage by the Communist Party against him and other Democratic Party members
1949 Published a book about Milan Hodža entitled Milan Hodža v Amerike
1951 Editor, Radio Free Europe, Czechoslovak Desk, New York
1951-1954 Associate Editor-In-Chief, RFE, Czechoslovak Desk, Munich, Germany
1954-1970 Associate Editor-In-Chief, RFE, Czechoslovak Desk, New York
1970-1974 Editor-In-Chief, RFE, Czechoslovak Desk, New York
20 September 1978 Died, New York
Scope and Content of Collection
Radio broadcast scripts, correspondence, writings, memoranda, reports, and printed matter, relating to Radio Free Europe broadcasts to Czechoslovakia.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Radio Free Europe; Radio broadcasting Czechoslovakia
Collection Contents
- Correspondence and brief writings, 1939-2000 and undated (Box 1-3)
  Contains correspondence mostly with Czechs and Slovaks in exile, many of them associated with RFE, or with Slovak or Czechoslovak émigré organizations in America; correspondence of Jarmila Múdra-Šebíková, after 1978, refers almost exclusively to Múdry
  Arranged in alphabetical and then chronological order
  - Abrahám, Samuel, 1993 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Belák-Berger, Karol, 1970-1977 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Belluš, Samuel, 1965-1976 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Beneš, Edvard, 1941, 1943 and 1974 (Folder 1: 3)
    Contains his speech, a photocopy of his letter, and an article about him
  - Bíl, Miloš (?), 1977 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Bosák, Michal J., 1958 and undated (Folder 1: 4)
    correspondence and reports
  - Collegium Carolinum, 1978 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Černý, Josef, 1971 (Folder 1: 4)
    obituary
  - Čvachovec, Karel, 1978 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Daruľová, Táňa, 2000 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Dellin, Eduard, 1951, 1977 and undated (Folder 1: 4)
  - Demeter, Ladislav, 1942-1976 and undated (Folder 1: 5)
    correspondence and obituaries
  - Duda, 1958 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Dulová, Lola, 1956 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Feierabend, Ladislav, 1961, 1964 and undated (Folder 1: 5)
  - Ferjenčík, Mikuláš, 1951-1988 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Fraštacký, Rudolf, 1963-1976 (Folder 1: 6)
    Includes articles by other authors
  - Havas, Emil, 1950 and undated (Folder 1: 7)
  - Hereky, Ernest, 1978 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Hodža, Fedor, 1950 and 1968 (Folder 1: 7)
    correspondence and an obituary
  - Horná, Dagmar and Miroslav Kusý, 1993 (Folder 1: 7)
  - Hrabík, Martin, 1973-1984 and undated (Folder 1: 8)
    Contains also an issue of Národné noviny from 1871, articles and news clippings
  - Jablonický, Jozef, 1967 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Johnson, Owen W., 1975 (Folder 1: 9)
    Contains also an autobiographical text by Múdry
  - Karčiš, Paul S., 1957 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Kirschbaum, Jozef, 1978 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Klimek, Peter, 1970 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Kováč, Juraj, 1963 (Folder 1: 9)
  - Kováčik, Ján, 1969-1975 (Folder 1: 10)
    Contains also letters, speeches and a report on church affairs in Czechoslovakia by Jozef Juráš
  - Krupa, J. Jaroslav, 1970 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Kružliak, Imrich, 1971-1977 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Lajda, Branislav, 1978 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Lavička, V., 1954-1955 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Lettrich, Jozef, 1954-1968 and undated (Folder 1: 13)
    Contains correspondence, writings and an RFE interview
  - Lettrichová, Irena, 1998 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Ličko, Miroslav, 1975-1999 and undated (Folder 1: 14)
    Includes eulogies for Múdry
  - Lukáč, Pavol, 1993-1994 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Malík, Josef, 1939-1941 and undated (Folder 1: 15)
    Contains letters to Edvard Beneš and others, and brief writings
  - Mamatey, Viktor, 1976-1978 (Folder 2: 1)
    Includes photocopies of published documents on M.R. Štefánik
  - Matica slovenská, Augustín Maťovčík, 1997-1998 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Mlynárik, Ján, undated (Folder 2: 1)
    Contains a typescript entitled Milan Rastislav Štefánik
  - Molitor, Ludwig, 1959 (Folder 2: 1)
    Contains a report on Molitor addressed to Thomas Myers
  - Mrázek, Jozef, 1967 and 1976 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Múdry-Šebík st., Michal, 1975 (Folder 2: 1)
  - Osuská, Pavla, 1956 and undated (Folder 2: 1)
    Includes typescripts for RFE programs
  - Osuský, Štefan, 1943-1956 and undated (Folder 2: 2)
    Contains also typescripts, speeches and press clippings
  - Paleček, A., 1977-1978 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Papánek, Ján, 1967 and 1978 (Folder 2: 3)
    Contains a photocopy of a letter to Mr. Čecha
  - Papánek, Štefan, 1977 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Pecháček, Jaroslav, 1967-1976 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Peroutka, Ferdinand, 1950-1973 (Folder 2: 5)
    Contains RFE related documents
  - Rayman, Karel, 1976 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Richter, V.A., 1978-1982 and undated (Folder 2: 6)
    Contains also Balada Generál Řimbuch, a poem in manuscript
  - Rudinský, Jozef, 1953-1956 and undated (Folder 2: 7)
  - Sidor, Karol, 1939 (Folder 2: 8)
    photocopies of a typescript entitled Moje poznámky k historickým dňom
  - Slezak, John / Slezák, Ján, 1949-1976 and undated (Folder 2.9-3: 1)
    Contains correspondence, interviews, speeches and related documents, as well as reminiscences on M.R. Štefánik, Štefan Slezák, and the Slovak National Uprising
  - Smerek, Ján, 1978 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Srba, Antonín, family, 1980 (Folder 3: 2)
    Contains correspondence and an obituary
  - Staško, Jozef, 1988 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Škarnicel, Belo, 1968-1975 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Škvor, Jiří, 1973-1978 and undated (Folder 3: 3)
  - Štefánek, Branislav, 1975-1979 and undated (Folder 3: 4)
  - Štefánek, Vladimír, 1971 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Švehla, František, 1975 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Ursíny, Ján, 1967 (Folder 3: 5)
    Contains Múdry's report on a meeting with Ursíny
  - Velvyslanectví ČSSR, Washington, D.C., 1974 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Vlčok, Štefan, 1970 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Voskovec, Jiří, 1974 (Folder 3: 6)
    An article dedicated to Egon Hostovský attached
  - Weber, Henry, 1951 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Zenkl, Peter, 1962 (Folder 3: 7)
    a report
  - Zibrín, Michal, undated (Folder 3: 7)
  - Zoder, undated (Folder 3: 7)
  - Unidentified letters and fragments, 1950-1978 and undated (Folder 3: 8)
- Alphabetical file, 1939-1979 and undated (Box 3-6)
  Contains mostly internal documents and correspondence of Slovak or Czechoslovak émigré organizations in America on political and cultural issues, and RFE materials on these issues
  - Communist Takeover and Occupation of Czechoslovakia, a U.S. congressional report, and reaction to the report from émigré organizations in the U.S. and from the Czechoslovak state organizations, 1954-1955 (Folder 3: 9)
    Contains correspondence, mostly between Múdry and Ján Kováčik, memoranda of the Slovak Lutheran Church representatives in America and by The Council of Free Czechoslovakia, press releases in the U.S. and in Czechoslovakia, RFE materials
  - Demokratická strana v exile, 1949 (Folder 3: 10)
    outline of a meeting agenda
  - Hodža, Milan, 1942-1978 and undated (Folder 3: 11, Folder 4: 1-5)
    Contains correspondence, published materials, Múdry's writings and other materials related to Hodža or on commemoration events for Hodža
  - Husák, Gustáv, 1969-1970 and undated (Folder 4: 6)
    Contains Múdry's article Czechoslovakia: Husák Takes the Helm, other articles in typescript and news clippings
  - National Alliance of Slovak Lutherans / Národný sväz slovenských evanjelikov, 1939-1947 and undated (Folder 4: 7)
    Contains a telegram from Edvard Beneš, internal documents, speeches, published matter, handwritten notes
  - Papánek, Ján, 1950-1978 and undated (Folder 5: 1-3)
    Contains articles and speeches, Múdry's notes and versions of a response article "Čs. zahraničná akcia v druhej svetovej vojne" a "Smear", osočujúca či očierňujúca kampaň
  - Political trials with the so-called bourgeois nationalists, 1951-1953 and undated (Folder 5.4-5: 5)
    Contains RFE broadcast materials and other reports, most of them prepared by Múdry, fragments of trial transcripts, news reports, periodicals
  - Rada slobodného Československa, 1975-1979 (Folder 5: 6)
    administrative correspondence and reports
  - Slovenská liga v Amerike / Slovak League of America, 1964 and undated (Folder 5: 7)
    correspondence and an interview
  - Slovenské národné sdruženie v Amerike, 1939-1942 and undated (Folder 5: 8)
    correspondence, proceedings and related documents
  - Společnost pro vědy a umění / Czechoslovak Society of Arts and Sciences in America, 1970-1974 and undated (Folder 5: 9)
    correspondence and promotional materials
  - Stála konferencia slovenských demokratických exulantov, 1963-1971 and undated (Folder 6: 1-8)
    Contains correspondence, presentation papers, minutes of meetings, resolutions and related materials
- Radio Free Europe materials, 1948-1978 and undated (Box 6-9)
  Contains administrative documents, and reports and memoranda on cooperation between Czechs and Slovaks in RFE, materials of organizations related to RFE (Voice of America, National Committee for Free Europe and other), broadcast scripts, correspondence with audience and related materials, promotional materials and publications, and other related documents.
  - Internal correspondence, reports and related materials, 1948-1953 (Folder 6: 9)
  - Memorandum of Slovak employees in RFE on founding a periodical, 1953-1954 and undated (Folder 6: 10)
  - Internal correspondence, reports and related materials, 1954 (Folder 6: 11)
    Contains a memorandum of "Slovak Catholics in RFE", documents protesting this memorandum, and other materials on cooperation between Czechs and Slovaks in RFE
  - Internal correspondence, reports and related materials, 1955-1965 (Folder 7: 1)
  - Internal correspondence, reports and related materials, 1966-1970 (Folder 7: 2)
  - Internal correspondence, reports and related materials, 1971-1978 (Folder 7: 3)
  - Internal correspondence, reports and related materials, and fragments of materials, undated (Folder 7: 4)
  - Correspondence with audience and related materials, 1954-1958 (Folder 7: 5)
  - Correspondence with audience and related materials, 1959-1963 and undated (Folder 7: 6)
  - Chilla, Jozef J., circa 1956-1958 and undated (Folder 7: 7)
    Contains Christmas Message scripts, correspondence and related materials
  - Leaflets, publications and other promotional materials, 1955-1956 and undated (Folder 7: 8)
  - Broadcast scripts and related materials, 1951 (Folder 7: 9)
  - Broadcast scripts and related materials, 1952 (Folder 8: 1-2)
  - Broadcast scripts and related materials, 1953 (Folder 8: 3)
  - Broadcast scripts and related materials, 1954 (Folder 8: 4)
  - Broadcast scripts and related materials, 1955 (Folder 8: 5)
  - Broadcast scripts and related materials, 1956 (Folder 8: 6)
  - Broadcast scripts and related materials, 1957 (Folder 8: 7, Folder 9: 1)
  - Broadcast scripts and related materials, 1958-1959 (Folder 9: 2)
  - Broadcast scripts and related materials, 1962-1964 (Folder 9: 3)
  - Broadcast scripts and related materials, 1965-1976 (Folder 9: 4)
  - Broadcast scripts and related materials, undated (Folder 9: 5-6)
- Writings by and about Múdry, 1942-1995 and undated (Box 9-11)
  Contains articles, lectures, RFE scripts and other writings by or probably by Múdry, publications, news clippings and other materials
  - Lectures and articles, 1942-1971 (Folder 9: 7)
  - Lectures and articles, 1973-1979 (Folder 10: 1)
  - Pomoc amerických Slovákov národu, 1968 (Folder 10: 2)
    lecture
  - Pomoc amerických Slovákov národu(?), undated (Folder 10: 3)
    Contains a typescript, parts úvod, Organizačné začiatky and Do prvej svetovej vojny
  - Pomoc amerických Slovákov národu(?), undated (Folder 10: 4)
    Contains a typescript, part Prvá svetová vojna
  - Report on the situation of the Protestant Church (Augsburg Denomination) / Zpráva o stave Evanjelickej cirkvi augšburského vyznania, 1954 and undated (Folder 10: 5)
    typescripts
  - Lectures, articles and other writings, undated (Folder 10: 6-11, Folder 11: 1-2)
  - Milan Hodža v Amerike, 1949 (Folder 11: 3)
    a book
  - Writings about Múdry, newspaper clippings, 1948-1995 and undated (Folder 11: 4)
- Miscellany, circa 1945-1994 (Box 11: 4)
  Contains news reports, books with dedications, photocopies of documents and fragments of materials
  - Miscellany, circa 1945-1994 (Folder 11: 5)
- News clippings and printed matter, circa 1940-1990 (Box 12)
  - News clippings, circa 1940-1978 (Folder 12: 1-4)
  - Miscellaneous printed matter and publications, circa 1942-1990 (Folder 12: 5)
    Contains periodicals and monographs, mostly on émigré affairs (Naše noviny, Kotva, on the Council of Free Czechoslovakia) and Czechoslovak domestic periodicals